Guide to the Charles R. Kuning Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, 1965-1985 MS2373
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Charles R. Kuning Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority collection
1965-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Kuning, Charles R.
MS2373
17.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains reports, transit studies, meeting agendas, marketing material, maps, memos, tour information, correspondence, photographs and construction drawings related to the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority. The material dates between 1965-1985. This material about WMATA relates specifically to research about other metropolitan transit systems and the early construction of the Metrorail system.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Reports and newsletters, and Drawings and technical specifications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles R. Kuning, May 9, 2018 (2018.018)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reports, transit studies, meeting agendas, marketing material, maps, memos, tour information, correspondence, photographs and construction drawings. The material dates from approximately 1965-1985. These are the records relate to the early days of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority including their research of other metropolitan transit systems and the early construction of the Metrorail system.
Biographical / Historical
While an engineering undergraduate, Charles R. Kuning worked from 1973 to 1976 for Cody Pfanstiehl as an unpaid intern and later as a contractor. During this time he provided pre-opening, construction tour guide services for the Office of Community Services which Pfanstiehl headed. This public outreach and information program took up to 20,000 members of the public, per year, on weekend hard hat tours, generally between Judiciary Square and Metro Center.
For Kuning's own education during that period, and up to around 1980, Kuning collected copies of board meeting packets (monthly and quarterly office reports, "Metroclips" newspaper clippings), public information/marketing materials (maps, brochures, "Metro Memo" newsletters) and other, generally letter-sized material. In addition, he collected a number of the B-sized (11"x17") plan books provided to potential bidders for tunnels, stations, bridges and other Metro construction projects.
Transportation -- Washington Metropolitan Area; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Transportation maps; Kuning, Charles R.
- Reports and newsletters, 1965-1985; Series 1; 7 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Organized alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Material in this series includes reports, transit studies, meeting agendas, marketing material, maps, memos, tour information, correspondence and photographs related to the early days of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority. Material dates between 1965-1985.
  - Action Reports, 1976-1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Action Reports, 1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Action Reports, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Action Reports, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Actions #1, 1974-1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agendas, 1974-1978; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports [1/2], 1969-1976; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports [2/2], 1977-1985; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Architecture and Comptroller Reports, 1976-1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - August Design and Construction Schedule Reports, 1976-1979; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baltimore Regional Transit Studies [1/2], 1975; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Baltimore Regional Transit Studies [2/2], 1976; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Baltimore [1/2], 1978-1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Baltimore [2/2], 1979-1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1974-1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bus: Public Hearing Notices Staff Reports, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cody Pfanstiehl, 1975-1982; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Comptroller Reports, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Comptroller and Marketing Reports, 1973-1976; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Construction and Ridership Status/Operation Highlights, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Construction Bi-Monthly Reports [1/2], 1975; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Construction Bi-Monthly [2/2], 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Construction Bi-Monthly Reports [1/2], 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Construction Bi-Monthly Reports [2/2], 1976; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Construction/development reports, 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Construction Quarterly Reports [1/2], 1979; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Construction Quarterly Reports [2/2], 1978; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cubic Western Operations Manual, 1984; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Design Criteria and Schedule, 1976; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Reports, 1974; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Impact Study, Undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Glossies [1/2], 1975-1980; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Glossies [2/2], 1972-1982; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Inside Metro, 1973-1981; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Management Reports, 1975; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Management Reports, 1975; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Management Reports, 1971-1975; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Management Reports, Undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Management Reports, 1974-1976; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Management Reports, 1975-1980; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Management Reports, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Management Reports, 1976-1977; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Maps, 1968-1970; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Marketing, Security and Secretary-Treasurer Reports, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Memos, 1980; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Memos and Information Routed to Me, 1976-1979; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Metro Marketing Plans, 1974-1976; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Metro Memo/Correspondence with Cody Pfanstiehl, 1972; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Metro Memo [1/2], 1971-1976; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Metro Memo [2/2], 1971-1974; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Metro Public Hearing Staff Reports, 1975-1979; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1974-1976; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Reports, 1975-1978; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - News Releases, 1973-1984; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Office of Engineering Bi-Monthly Reports, 1977-1978; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Office of Engineering Bi-Monthly Reports, 1976; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Office of Engineering Reports, 1972-1976; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Office of Program Control Reports, 1979-1981; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Operators Guides and WMATA Alternative Plans, 1975-1977; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Papers, 1969-1979; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Pre-opening information/job application, 1974; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Press, 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Public Hearing Notices Metro, 1973-1981; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Quarterly Performance Report, 1980; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Rail Car Availability, 1979; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - San Francisco, Atlanta, Chicago, Undated; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Sidewalk Superintendent, 1974-1979; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Tabulation of Bids, 1975-1980; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Tour Information, 1973-1979; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Tours: Thank You Letters, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Transit Plans, 1974-1977; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Various Departmental Reports, 1974-1979; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Drawings and technical specifications, 1970-1980; Series 2; 10.5 Linear Feet
  Materials in this series include technical specification drawings for building the early Metrorail system. Materials date between 1970-1980.
  Organized chronologically.
  - Request for the Technical Proposal Automatic Train Control and Communications Part III of III 2Z2011, 1970; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Index of Drawings, 1970; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Invitation for Bid Communications 1Z2021, 1971; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Request for Technical Proposal Rapid Transit Cars Part III Drawings 2Z8061, 1971; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Index of Directive Drawings, 1972-1975; Series 2 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Section C-9 Huntington Route 1C0091, 1972-1975; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Single Sheet - Double-Swing Gate, 1973; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Index of Directive Drawings, 1974; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - L'Enfant Plaza Station, 1974; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Memos, 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Huntington Route, 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Section TW3 Trackwork-3 Informatino Drawings 1Z4083, 1976; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Communications 1Z2024, 1977; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Trackwork-4 Installation 1Z4084, 1977; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Section FK-2 Vienna Route 1K3021, 1977; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Section C-10c Huntington Route 1C0103, 1977; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Huntington Route 1C0101, 1977; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Rockville Route, 1977; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Glenmont Route Engineering Analysis Sections B009, B010, and B011, 1977; Series 2 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Key Plan of System and General Construction Site Plan, 1977-1981; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Section C-10b Huntington - Springfield Routes 1C0102, 1978; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Section A-14 Rockville Route 1AO141, 1978; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Metro Status, 1978; Series 2 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Section C-10b Huntington-Springfield Routes 1C0102, 1978; Series 2 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Station Platform Shelters Installation 1Z309C, 1979; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Substation Installation Stage SSI-5 1A1045, 1979; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Trackwork-6 Installation 1Z4086, 1980; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Metro System Maps - 5 MM-5 2Z409G, 1981; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Vienna Route Yeonas Drive Tie Breaker Station 1K0074, 1981; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Vienna Route Prosperity Avenue Tie Breaker Station 1K0075, 1981; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Section K-7c Vienna Route Barbour Road Traction Power Substation 1K0073, 1981; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - TG-5A Tunnel & R.O.W. Graphics 5A 1Z009G, 1981; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Contrast specifications for the fabrication and installation of the escalators -L 1Z405L, 1981; Series 2 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Section C-10e Huntington-Springfield Routes 1C0105, 1981; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Eisenhower Avenue Station Landscaping 1C3102, 1981; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Drawings Escalators-L 1Z405L, 1981; Series 2 (Box 21, Folder 1)